in this video we're going to talk about
the harmonic series and if it's
convergent or divergent
so consider the series which starts from
1 and goes to infinity of the sequence 1
over n so if we list out the terms when
n is one it's just going to be one when
n is two it's one half
and then plus a third
plus a fourth
and plus one fifth and so forth
now if you keep adding
these terms you'll realize that the sum
will continue to increase it's going to
get bigger and bigger and bigger and
bigger it's not going to converge to a
single value if you just add it
and so just by doing that it tells you
that this series
is divergent
now if you're thinking about doing the
divergence test
to prove that it's divergent
it's not really going to work out too
well
so if we take the limit as n approaches
infinity for a sub n
so a sub n is one over n
this will equal zero
now for the divergence test to work
if it doesn't equal zero the limit
then
the series diverges but if it equals
zero
well it's inconclusive the series it may
converge
or it may
diverge
so the divergence test won't help us for
this example
but another test that we could use
is the integral test
now if we take the integral let's say
from
one to infinity
of f of x dx
if this integral is convergent
then
the series
the corresponding series
is also
convergent
likewise if the integral test fails if
it's divergent then the series will be
divergent
so the corresponding function for f of x
is going to be 1 over x
so let's integrate it from 1 to infinity
the anti-derivative of one over x is ln
x
and
we can't really use the infinity symbol
so i'm going to use some constant a with
the limit
as
a approaches infinity since we have an
improper integral
and so this is going to be equal to
the limit as a approaches infinity
the natural log of a
minus the natural log of 1.
so the limit as a approaches infinity of
ln a
what is that equal to
well the natural log of infinity is
going to be a large number that's still
going to be infinity
and ln 1 is zero
so the limit i mean not the limit but
the integral
of one over x from one to infinity is
divergent
because
we didn't get a finite answer
our answer is infinity
so because
according to the integral test the
integral from one to infinity is
divergent then the series must also be
divergent so that's another way in which
you could show
that the harmonic series is diverging
you